[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net sc radio is brought to you
by the ieee computer society by ieee
software magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
hello everyone today we welcome multiple
gears to our show
michael is a front-end developer
passionate about user
interfaces he has worked on many
e-commerce projects in the past decade
michael shares his learnings by way of
conference talks
and by running a site microfrontends.org
he also has a book in progress on the
same topic welcome to the show michael
so happy to have you here my pleasure
thanks
so michael let's jump right into it what
are microfront ends
the microphone is architecture is a way
of
dividing an application into multiple
parts that can be worked upon
independently
so let me give you an example we are
building e-commerce systems
and in our projects we have different
teams working on different parts of the
e-commerce system so we have one team
that only does
search we have the we have another team
that
does the product detail page and we have
a third team that
handles the complete checkout process
and all of these teams have their own
application
they have their own deployment process
they have their own database in their
own front end
and can work independently from each
other and only integrate in the front
end so this is what most people call
microfrontence or the microphone its
architecture
so you mean the front end is a piece of
the entire
vertical slice yes so as opposed to just
micro services in the past where only
the back end
teams had the vertical slice but the
front end was one big layer
yes when you compare it to microservices
you can see it as microservices with an
integrated ui
so having in the ui inside of each
microservice and then integrating on the
ui level and not on an api
level in the backend so why is that good
what was wrong with
having a monolithic ui talking to many
microservices
basically the same reasons why you
wanted to
move from a monolithic backend to
microservices applied to the front end
as well so having a monolithic front end
at a certain size
creates organizational issues so having
10 or 15 people working on one code base
for the front end
can become a challenge and another
reason is
that when you create vertical slices
which include the user interface and
also the database the business logic and
everything
beside it you are able to have
cross-functional teams that
are able to work faster because everyone
necessary for creating a feature is
inside of this team
okay let's take a step back and look at
what is the situation before
microfrontends
so you have one ui team what else is
part of that team
what are the skill sets that that team
needed to have
so in a layered architecture you have a
dedicated frontend team that handles
everything in the front end so they
they picked a javascript framework for
example
and all of these people build a huge
application with this javascript
framework and
the front-end team gets its data from
the microservices underneath
it and in many cases you have a back-end
for front-end which aggregates
or hides the microservices architecture
and delivers the data through the front
end as the front-end people need it and
you have dedicated people in this
microsoft services
that are working on the backend michael
what is a back-end for front type
concept that you mention
what problem does it solve so the
concept back-end for front-ends
is a is a way to aggregate data from a
microservice architecture
so that the front and front-end team
could use it so the front-end the people
working on the front end
don't have to know about how many
microservices are there
and which microservices which
microservice is responsible for what
um they get an aggregated view through
the layer the back-end for front-end
layers it sits
between the front and the back-end is
that a replacement for the typical way
you would do it by using rest apis
so a back-end for front-end can be a set
of rest apis but it aggregates
and normalizes these apis for
the front team so how is the interaction
between the frontend
team and the different microservices
team in that case
so if you're building a feature that is
that only involves one micro service or
only involves
making one change inside of the front
end everything is fine so
the front end team can make its change
and everything is pretty
but if you have a feature and most
features are structured this this way
where you need a change on the backend
maybe you need a new field in the
database
and the field in the database should
also be visible in the front end
then multiple teams have to connect so
the
back-end team has to make the change the
front-end team has to make the ui
adaption to show the new value
and maybe also the front-end for back
and see the interface layer between
these two
has to be updated to to add this data
and
talking between these different teams is
something that's expensive
and the communication between these
teams is something that's very expensive
in most companies not because it's
complicated but because it takes time so
you have to arrange a meeting
talk to the other team say that you need
a new field the other team
has to put this task in its backlog and
the other
the front team has to wait for the data
becoming available
and with introducing cross-functional
teams or end-to-end teams
where all people from front-end to
back-end are inside of one team
you can eliminate this talking to each
other
eliminate the coordination between
different teams
so the driver for micro front end sounds
like mainly is the team structure
so are micro services a prereq for
building micro front ends
in a certain way i would say yes so at
least when we
when you build the microphones
architecture in the way i just described
so having a team that
does front end and also does back end
you can do micro front ends only on the
front end so if you're having
a large react application for example
and you
want to parallelize development inside
of this react application you can
just split the front end and let the
back end stay as it is
so it's not a requirement to use the
microservices style architecture also in
the back end
but most companies that introduce it do
it to
gain the organizational benefits can you
give us some examples of customers that
are developing or have developed with
microfountains
yes so there are a lot of e-commerce
companies that have adopted
this architecture so there's a european
retailer called zelendo which
structured their application in this way
also ikea's
new online platform is built using micro
microfrondes approach but there are also
other companies like the sports
streaming
service the zone or the job marketplace
company stepstone
um or even bigger companies like sap
they've created microfondants library
at the end of last year published it i
have seen some presentations by this on
i think on o'reilly as well are you
familiar with their work
yes luca the architect from the zone
is very active in this community and um
shares a lot of their learnings
so do customers start with
microfrontends or is that something that
they actually refactor to
so since microfundance is an
architecture for scaling development
i haven't seen many smaller startup
companies that
started with a microfinance approach so
most cases i've seen the companies had a
existing monolith
knew their business model and then split
it into individual parts
to to grow their development and
parallelize
their teams so we talked a little bit on
the team structure
that caused the reason to move to micro
frontends
we'll talk more about how teams will now
be structures with micro
front tents in place but before that
let's continue
our discussion on the skill sets that we
started you mentioned that
prior to micro front ends a lot of teams
built
the front the ui using javascript what
else what are the technologies that
would you expect
front-end developers to have so if
you're doing the microphones approach
end-to-end
you are suddenly working not only with
other frontal developers but also with
back-end developers you're talking about
apis
and in our projects i found it very
inspiring to see people getting out of
their comfort zone so
back-end developers being able to to
look at the front end or to modify the
front end but the same for 400
developers so from the developers
getting closer
to the backend so removing the front and
back end gap we
introduced over the last years another
skill every developer should have
is similar with the microphone and
architecture you're
now building a distributed system so
you're not
the software you're building is part of
a larger system and you have to
understand
how these parts play together so what
user interface part it
integrates or interacts with another
user interface part from another team
for example
so michael that means that ui developers
can no longer just focus on front-end
technologies
which is a big complex area in itself
but now i have to understand the entire
system
as well as the fact that it's
distributed which introduces a lot of
complexity
so does this impact their skills and
does this impact the expertise that they
have to gather and dilute the
functionality in other ways
so yes in general you could say that
front-end developers now have more tasks
than
compared to a pure front-end team so
they're moving from being a front-end
specialist to
more of a generalist that also knows
other parts of the system
another effect we see in these teams is
that
you all of a sudden you don't have a
team of 10 49 developers for example but
you have two front-end developers
in five teams and these front-end
developers are not able to
specialize in specific areas of the
front-end like you have one for that
developers
who's very good at integration testing
for example and you have another
developer that understands the redux
store
very very well the front developers in
these teams
have to have a broader understanding
because
they are for example two people in the
bigger team of
mostly back-end developers let's let's
continue with the team
for a little bit more and then we'll get
to technology now we talked about the
front-end developers what
impact does microfront ends have on the
backend developers that are now part of
the team
do they have to get additional skills
you can
compare to the devops movement where
back-end developers
were suddenly also required to also
acquire tasks
that enable them to run their own
infrastructure for example on
on the cloud system and the same way
with microphone and this back-end
developers now have to expand
and now can expand their horizon to the
front end so
also understanding what goes on in the
front end that that doesn't mean that
everyone on the team has to know
everything by heart but
the area and the area of the system
and the technologies involved are
getting broader
so there's more awareness in this
cross-functional team
in both directions what about ui design
engineers
having a good strategy for ui design
and having a centralized design system
for example is very
crucial so in all of our projects we are
we
set up a design system from the start so
all applications use the same ui
building blocks
for the user interface they create this
ensures that
the end product which is made up of
different applications
has a similar look and feel to the end
user
so in an optimal world we would also
have
ux designers inside of every team but
in our projects we we had one project
where we achieved this
and we had enough resources to to staff
all teams with ux
designer but you can also have a
centralized design team for example that
builds
a pattern library a style guide that
other teams can
use and these designers can support
these teams in building user interfaces
that feel alike
what about the role of front-end leads
in this team structure
so since since they are not talking
about one big front-end but
have multiple smaller front ends there's
not as much
need for having a strong tech lead um
because you have only
two or three people working on the front
end so the need for having a strong lead
decreases but you still have inter-team
topics
uh where all teams should should agree
upon so having a common strategy
to do accessibility to do performance
testing for example
is something all teams have to
coordinate upon
and in our projects we have people like
we call them front-end architects which
try to
create a common vision across all of
these teams
so now you have front-end architects
that are coordinating
or giving a common vision to multiple
teams how is that typically coordinated
so the main focus of this microphone is
architecture is having teams
being able to run on their own so having
their own systems making their own
technology decisions and deploying the
application
but you definitely need coordination
between
these pro but since you don't want to
reinvent
the wheel you have the need for
exchanging best practices
exchanging information between people
from the same profession across multiple
teams so
a common pattern for for solving this is
having guilds
so having fronted developers from all of
the teams
come together weekly for example and
talk to each other discuss
common topics like how to solve this
kind of integration problem
or what performance best practices all
teams should adopt
and we don't have this only for
front-end we also have this for
a specific kind of database for example
or for
search engine optimization or for doing
analytics
properly so you have people from
different teams that come together on a
regular basis
to exchange information besides best
practices i assume there are shared
components and share libraries
for let's say authentication or
monitoring
is that right and how are those
owned and coordinated and shared
so in general we try to avoid
introducing shared libraries or
shared infrastructure systems because
they can introduce
coupling but we also have talked about
the pattern library or design system
earlier so
this is a shared piece of software that
all that all teams can pull
into their application to accomplish
a coherent user interface for example
and there are other topics like
how to do authentication you don't want
the user to have to log in with its
password and user interface into
each individual microfrontend in this
scenarios we have one team
that does the authentication has
the concept of a user and this team
provides the login information for
example via jwt token
to the other teams you also mentioned
infrastructure so
we also have a common logging service
for example
which is owned and hosted and maintained
by one team and other teams can
use this system as a logging service so
that not all teams have to build up
their own infrastructure
so you're recommending an approach where
there is not one infrastructure team
each team that is owning a microphone 10
also owns additional pieces or
additional services that other teams can
leverage
why is that what is wrong with having an
infrastructure team
so both approaches are valid and i see
many companies
having dedicated infrastructure teams so
both approaches are valid and
i've also seen a lot of companies having
dedicated infrastructure teams
in our projects we try to have all teams
centered around a specific customer
focus so we have the search team for
example
which solves the searching need from the
customer and
a horizontal team like for example in it
an infrastructure team
doesn't directly solve a need for the
customer it indirectly solves it
through providing tools for the feature
team to do their job
but we see value in not
introducing teams that are not directly
connected to the customer
i see so sounds like the benefit of
microphone tens is twofold
one is in the organizational structure
and communication reducing communication
needs across multiple teams
but also you see value in having each
team
actually have a complete customer focus
which pushes them to build better
product is that
is that where you're getting at yes in
many projects we are doing the
creating direct value for the customer
reason is one of the main arguments
so let's talk about cicd
i suppose having the entire team focused
on one area
actually helps with the testing
integration and deployment as well
do you want to comment on that yes so in
practice
all teams have their own cicd pipelines
so when they make a change they do
that they test their part of the user
interface and the pipeline also rolls
out
the new software to production and
this these pipelines shouldn't be
connected in any ways to
to ensure the independence there might
also be need for testing
the interfaces between the teams so
having testing the customer journey for
example going from the home page to
the product page to through the checkout
to the confirmation page
but these types of tests where you have
to ensure that everything fits together
are not as many in our projects so
all teams test their their own
application and maybe they test the
system
they integrate with directly but we
don't see
need for having a massive amount of
cross team testing
what about the ownership for production
support does that then lie with the
micro front end team as well yes when
the when you go the full stack approach
so
having a team being responsible from
user interface to the database
they are also responsible for running
their own system so
we implement a you build it you under
wanted approach
where if something goes wrong on the
weekend someone
from the team's page and has to fix the
problem to get it
right up and running again so it sounds
like the push to microphone tenses
multi-fold one is organizational
structure reducing communication
increasing independence allowing for
customer focus for every team then the
last one
is just in the cicd pipelines much
easier to
slice it vertically and then support it
as well in production
so there seems to be a lot of benefits
before we go on to the technologies what
are the cons
so compared to monolithic application
doing this
vertical end to end split requires a lot
of coordination you have to find
the right boundaries you're suddenly
running
a distributed system which is far more
complex to run
than just having one 400 team and one
backend team for example
you're introducing technical complexity
to achieve more development speed okay
we'll get back to some more discussion
on the pros and cons in a bit but let's
talk about technology so you set you
started to say you're
adding technical complexity so how are
these
multiple microfront tents now fused
together to
form a cohesive application let's start
with that what are the options to do
that
yeah so the front integration part is
where it's starting to get interesting
so
that microphone is not a specific
technology it doesn't require a specific
technology and
the technical solution you need for
integrating the user interface
heavily depends on the application
you're building so if you're building a
server-side rendered application maybe a
ruby on rails application
you need a service or piece of
infrastructure
that takes the html snippets from the
different teams
composes them together and delivers them
to the end users so the end user sees
a com it's complete picture with user
interface parts
from all of these teams if you're
running a fully client-side rendered
application like
having multiple teams developing
different react applications
that should be integrated in the front
end the solution is quite different so
you don't need
side markup generation because markup is
only generated on the client
so if you're generating your markup on
the client side
maybe with having multiple teams
developing react applications
these teams would integrate client side
so
a solution that you could use would be
web components for example so having is
the user interface
from one team being wrapped in a web
component and having the web component
be the contract for the other teams so
if you're rendering your markup on the
client side you would integrate you
would also do the integration
on the client side so you would have
multiple teams all developing
their own react applications or small ui
parts that are react applications in and
of themselves
and these teams would have to come up
with a contract
to use the interface user interface from
the novel team
and a good way for doing this would be
to use sub components as a technical
standard
that all teams can agree upon let's go
slowly
you talked about server side rendered
and with an example of ruby on rails and
then you talked about
teams developing with react is it
possible first of all that you have some
teams developing with the server side
rendering technology and some with
javascript and react yes you can of
course
mix and match these approaches so having
one team only doing client-side
rendering and another team doing
server-side rendering
as long as your integration techniques
support talking to each other so let's
talk more about
web components how are the requirements
for the web components defined
and what if the needs change the teams
then still have to communicate and
coordinate with each other
so we are using web components as a
neutral
integration format which you can expose
your application
in so let me give you an example maybe
we have a team
which which has the job of delivering a
recommendation strip
that other teams can use inside of the
e-commerce system and this team
creates a web component which it
registers globally
inside of the browser and the web
component
and this team the the recommendation
team
tells the name and maybe attributes you
can pass into the sub components
to the other teams and as long as the
name of the web component and the
attributes so the signature of the web
components don't change
both teams are free to develop evolve
their parts of the application so the
recommendation team can
implement smarter algorithms do a nicer
view of
the recommendation strip for example and
they can do everything they want as long
as they don't change
the interface so the technical api
between the streams
so web components are one way of
composing
from front-ends from multiple teams
what are the other ways of composing the
ui
let's let's start with server-side
rendered applications
yeah so with server-side rendering there
are different options so
i've seen companies building their own
assembly proxy so
having one team deliver a page but
this page is not complete but it
requires insertion of
markup fragments so we call them
fragments
from other teams and all the markup
that's generated server side passes
through this assembly service which
looks for the placeholders
and fetches the markup from the other
teams and then delivers the complete
page you can do this with standard nginx
by activating its ssi feature
which does this concatenation of markup
but there are also other solutions
like folks from the lando the
german retailer developed a tool which
is called taylor
and there are other libraries like
podium for example
um which also do this assembly
and most if you're using a cdn most cdns
implement a feature which is called esi
which is quite similar to the ssi
feature i talked about in
in nginx which also does this assembly
but on the edge so
just before your pages are delivered
from your content delivery network
the other fragments of content are
fetched and moved in and
assembled what does ssi stand for ssi is
short for service site includes an esi
is short for edge site includes so one
happens on
the server on your web server inside of
your data center and the edge side
includes more of a cdn feature
so in both these cases as well as web
components we are still talking of a
single page
that has ui from multiple front micro
front end teams
yes so when we're talking about assembly
uh or when we're talking about
composition
with ssi for example or with web
components we are talking about how to
integrate
user interface paths from multiple teams
into one view
but there's also another type of
integration which is called routing
where you integrate between pages of
different teams so as in my example from
earlier
when you're building an online shop and
you have a checkout team for example and
you have
a search team these teams the largest
part of their team uis are
individual pages so you have the search
page
the checkout team maybe as a card page
and payment pages and other pages
and to integrate on page level
we you need to use routing so a
classical server way
would be to have a load balancer or
having something like nginx
which does url based routing so every
all urls
starting with search for example go to
the search team all urls
starting with checkout go to the
checkout team
this works very well when you're
generating server side but if you're
trying to build a unified single page
application so having a single page
application
which consists of multiple single page
applications
inside of the browser so having a single
page application from team checkout
having a single page application from
team search
you need to teach the browser a way
to move from one single page application
to another single page application
without doing
a hard reload and they're also libraries
that implement this
routing on top of single page
applications the most popular one is
a library which is called single spa
hiring a software engineer then we
recommend working with g2i
g2i is the most effective way to
discover talented and pre-vetted
engineers for every project
g2i vets their talent pool through
technical interviews and various code
challenges which are graded by actual
engineers
saving you time and guaranteeing you top
quality through their transparent
grading
they specialize in react react native
and node.js
interested in learning more then go to
g2i.co
okay all right so one single page
can have fragments from different micro
front-end schemes
multiple pages there can be routing
between multiple pages
where the entire the browser refreshes
it just
loads the new page and then the last
option
is when you're trying to actually put
together multiple single page
multiple spa applications together and
you do not
want the refresh of the browser are
those those three things that you talked
about
yes okay so web components is for
composing potentially one page with
multiple fragments and on the routing
now on the server
side rendered applications let's talk
about the technical
op option to support the routing and
navigation
between these do you need to introduce
additional framework
to allow for that routing okay so so
doing server side routing requires all
requests
going through one central place which
does the routing so
when you want to do the routing you're
on a path base
so all urls starting with one prefix go
to one team and all url starting with
another prefix
go to another team you need a single
piece of infrastructure that handles
this and
also contains this routing logic which
prefix is responsible for which team
we call this in layer fronted proxy in
our projects which can be
a standard nginx web server for example
or with a configuration for these
different paths
and in the case of multiple single page
applications that come together how do
you
how do you still integrate so that the
experience does not degrade
so if we move the routing to the front
end with a library
like single sba for example the routing
logic suddenly moves
to the front end and you introduce a
single point of failure so all incoming
requests
go to what we call an application shell
so having
a minimalistic html file with
this routing logic which knows okay when
the incoming url starts with this
prefix parameter i have to load single
page
the single page app from one team
instantiate it
so it comes to life and if you break
this application shell
and if this application shall fail fails
the application doesn't work the
complete application
doesn't work anymore so you introduce a
single piece of infrastructure which is
quite critical and someone has to own
and maintain
this application shell and i suppose one
of the microphone 10 teams would have to
own up
and support this shell as well yes or if
you go with the platform team maybe the
platform team hosts this
but yes what is the approach that you've
taken in your projects
so in our projects we go with an
approach we call
linked single page apps so each team can
develop a single page app you may
have a single page app for the checkout
for example
but when you cross team boundaries so
when the team goes from search to the
product page
they do a hard reload so the user
interface inside of the search
can be client-side rendered and quick
but moving from one team to another
introduces a reload which if your
application
renders quickly might not be a huge
huge negative impact to your customer so
what was the evaluation process for you
to choose this approach versus
having it more complex so as we work in
e-commerce it's crucial for us to
deliver
fast page load speed so server rendering
is
quite important for the product page
product list pages and also search
engine optimization
was was a very high goal so this this
leads us to opting for server rendering
and at least in the projects we've built
and up until now
the complexity of introducing a shared
application shell on top of server side
rendering
so having universal rendering with an
application shell
introduced a high amount of complexity
which we avoided we opted for a simpler
approach with linked single page
applications
and didn't implement the application
shell okay michael but let's
introduce a little more context on
universal rendering
you talked about a new term there please
help us understand what you mean by
universal rendering
yeah so the term universal rendering or
isomorphic applications isomorphic
rendering isomorphic javascript
describes a technique
where the front end can be rendered in
the client but you can use the same code
also running on the server so modern
javascript frameworks
call this feature server-side rendering
as a feature
for a javascript application for example
teams
in our projects can opt to also do
server-side rendering on top of
client-side rendering
to get the benefits of a faster first
page load for example and being able to
be indexed
by search engines better let's talk
about events a little bit
other use cases that require microfront
terms to react for erectile events from
another
microfronton yes so communication is
also an important topics
when we are talking about the pay on
page level
you have communication via the ul so you
have a search page
and the team owning the search page has
to know the url scheme
for the product detail page so they add
an sku parameter
to the url of the product page and this
is already
a kind of communication so communicating
via url this is
a really restful way of communication
but when you have multiple user
interfaces from different teams on one
page
you sometimes also have the need for
talking
across these user interface parts so let
me give you an example on the product
page
you may have product page with a buy
button and the buy button is owned by
the checkout team so when you click the
buy button the checkout is modified
but you may also have other user
interface elements
or other fragments from the checkout
team on the same page so you might have
a mini mini basket so if you click on
the buy button for a product
product you want the mini basket to
reflect the change but
both uis are separated so you have one
microphone and showing the button you
have another microphone and showing the
mini card and you need some kind of
communication between those two and a
system you could use which is already
present in all browsers
is using custom browser events so like
emitting
a click event you can emit a specific
event for
the use case the user just just did so
the button can emit a product added to
basket event and other
microphones can listen to it and react
okay so let's summarize here
there are many ways to compose the
application
from ui from the multiple microfrontend
themes
you could have web components that
contribute to a single page
you could do routing between multiple
pages
with hard refreshes using links you
could also have some kind of shell layer
then that can integrate with multiple
single page applications so that there
is no need to do a hard
refresh when you're navigating between
micro front ends however that does
introduce that
additional layer the last thing we
talked about
was events and the ability to
potentially react to events between
different micro front ends as well
is there any other topic for the
technology aspect that you would like to
cover
from a front integration perspective i
think we covered
all of them so having routing having
composition and also having strategies
for
doing communication so in practice you
might also need
we just we talked about authentication
before you need a
common way for teams to access
login information for example or maybe
you want to introduce
central headers for example that
indicate which country
the user is in or which environment your
application is deployed to so the other
context information that might also be
interesting to
think about before you're building an
application so let's
move into the mori discussion on the
pros and cons
we did talk about the pros and we'll
come back to that
what about more on the cons let's talk
about performance
now you have multiple deployments and
you have navigation
and routing can you talk about what this
means to performance
yeah so when you're integrating on the
server side they
and you don't have much client-side code
i think the performance aspects
are negligible so you need a server-side
markup concatenation which
should be fast but the overall load time
of the page
shouldn't be different from a page which
is built by a monolithic application for
example
if you're doing the client-side
integration part which where all teams
use
javascript frameworks or maybe use
different javascript frameworks you
introduce overhead so
the browser has to load the vendor codes
the react runtime for example for all of
these teams
and you have different options of
going with this so so most projects i've
seen
all teams agree upon one standard way
or one standard framework to use so
unless one team has
some very serious reason to deviate from
the standard
um all teams use for example react and
then it becomes easy to
put the react runtime or multiple
versions of the react run
time inside of a shared cdn for example
and let teams link to it and if multiple
teams use
the same version of react for example
it's only downloaded once and not
downloaded
for every microphone so this is one way
of achieving
of improving the performance and
reducing the overhead
and another quite interesting trend is
that over the last years
we've seen front-end frameworks that
don't introduce a runtime at all so
frameworks like swelt for example or
stencil
are frameworks that don't have a large
runtime as you know from react or vue.js
or angular
they just compile to very
straightforward javascript code which
which grows linear to the amount of
features you build so if you're building
a hello world
application in swelt the javascript
associated with it
is very very small and if you have
multiple teams
building microphones with tools like
this you
there's not much extra overhead compared
to monolithic application
so the overhead you talked about was
mainly around the amount of javascript
that has to be downloaded and
potentially when you're navigating
between multiple micro front ends
you would be downloading the javascript
multiple times
using new frameworks like swelt which
have much reduced amount of javascript
automatically helps that was your point
yes
there's also if you want to achieve
isolation on style level you also
talk about redundant css
or styling code so if you're having a
pattern library and all teams
pull their css for a button for example
from the pattern library
prefix it and bundle it in their own
style sheet you also have introduced
redundant styles
but in practice this is not a huge issue
when it comes to load performance
because
cs browsers are able to pass css very
fast brothers are able to
process css in a very fast way compared
to the overhead javascript introduces
what about usability cons so you did
talk about one where potentially
navigating
between multiple microphone turns
requires refreshes
what other impacts to usability do you
have you observed and what are some ways
to mitigate it
yeah so having a shared design system
and
having a good concept for user
experience
that all teams adhere to is very
critical so as i said we
introduce a design system with all
microphones projects we do because
changing the user experience or changing
the ui
a couple months later to unify all of
the user interface parts is quite a
challenging job but yes you have the
the challenge that multiple teams build
applications
in their own way and you have to talk
about should the submit button be on the
left
side on the right side should the
labeling on the button be capitalized or
not and
you have to define these aspects more
thoroughly compared to a monolithic
application where
you have one team and the team
implicitly knows how to do stuff
and in this way you wouldn't have to
have a widget
or have a solid documentation on it and
so it is certainly important for the
different teams
to talk to each other to understand the
different design patterns
in this case and we did talk about that
earlier you mentioned that
you encourage weekly guild meetings is
that the term you used
so the team guild or guild meetings
where people from the same profession
but from different teams come together
as a term
i guess spotify introduced a couple of
years ago
maybe you can add a link to the show
notes they have a quite good
documentation on
their team structure which is quite
which is quite similar to what we now
call microphone in so they
had an organization which is structured
quite similar
to the things we just talked about in
the microfinance concept but
they did it much earlier and shared
their experiences with it and one of
these
learnings is having people could people
from different teams
connect with each other helps building
better products
is it ever a good idea to start with a
microbrunten based approach
all projects i know that implemented
microphones come
from at least an earlier system mostly a
monolithic system
where the developers and architects that
work on it
had a very good understanding on how
good cuts and good boundaries could be
established
inside of this application so if you're
a startup and you don't know how your
final product
will look i think it's not helpful to
introduce
a microphone it's architecture with
these solid boundaries that are
that are organized around so i think
it's not a good idea
to start with a micro fondant
architecture
so if you're a startup and you don't
know how your final product
will look like maybe you have to change
plans along the way
i think implementing a microphone
can stand in your way because you might
have to change team boundaries
a lot of times as your product is
changing and
changing team boundaries is something
which is
very complex and very hard to do so the
microphone
architecture optimizes to create value
inside of these boundaries but
i would also would only
implement it when you're confident about
your boundaries
that said how do you start maybe with
the
monolithic front-end but with the
recognition that
in the future you might want to refactor
to a microfront-end architecture what
principles do you have to keep in mind
in that case
yes so even if you start building a
model is
structuring your monolith in a way
that acknowledges boundaries and
even if you start with the monolith you
can modularize it in a way that it that
makes it easy to
do a hard cut later on so divide your
monolith
into two different systems along the
line of
split up your monoliths in the middle
for example
and having one set of pages be in one
application and another set of
applications be in another part of the
application and maybe figure out
which parts should be fragments that the
other my application
needs to integrate so it's definitely
possible if you have an eye on
the structure from the start to create
an application which is
easier to split later on so being aware
of the functional boundaries that make
sense
what about in terms of the
infrastructure or technologies that they
adopt
is there any guidance so since the
microphones architecture doesn't make
any assumptions on if your application
is server-side clients i don't know what
framework you're using i think you're
pretty good you're pretty open to using
the best tool
for the job and later on find an
integration solution
that fits your approach are you aware of
any cases where people did bill with
microfrontends and then realized that
that might have been a mistake or an
overkill
i've read a blog post from a gaming
company i'm
i don't know the name on top of my head
but they
introduced a micros a microphone its
application a few years ago
and it didn't have strong guidelines on
what these themes what tech stack these
teams
could use and they had massive issues
with
having a lot of javascript being loaded
for all users
which resulted in a very slow user
experience and they moved away
from this microphone its architecture to
a more monolithic approach
to solve these issues so it certainly
sounds like
you know the overarching goals is
team independence letting people choose
their own technologies
letting people manage their own
application
part of the application end to end
however there are other needs to
communicate between
teams to ensure that the design is
consistent
there are some cons with respect to
paying a lot of attention to ensuring
that
the performance is adequate and the
usability is adequate
anything else you want to summarize this
section with on the pros and cons
oh i think it's a pretty good summary of
the important parts
of the microphone its architecture so
michael let's talk more
about your book what were your goals in
writing this book
so as we started building our first
applications following
these architectures so back in the day i
think in 2014 we did our first project
and at this time the term microphone is
wasn't around and this
there was nothing to to google for
solving an integration of multiple
applications and what challenges
this introduces so so with the book i've
written over the last year
um i'm trying to address all of the
things
we learned the hard way in our journey
on building
different applications using this
architecture and
yeah so you could say the book i've
written
is the book i wanted to have back then
in 2014 when we got started so i hope
there's there are lessons in there there
are techniques in there that can help
other people
who want to adopt this architecture so
that they don't have to solve
the same problems from the start but are
aware of
some pitfalls and see solutions for the
challenges
they come across i noticed you had a lot
of code samples in your book
how are you expecting readers to use
those code samples
yes so i love as a developer i love code
obviously and throughout the book you're
building
an e-commerce application so we start
with a pretty simple product detail page
and expand this product detail page
by adding new features introducing new
teams introducing communication patterns
for example but also solving performance
issues
and the sample code for this book is
available on my github repository but
it's also hosted on a site
which is called the tractor.store which
we can
link in the uh in the show notes and
as you follow the chapter in the book
you can run your code on
on your machine but you can also go
directly to the browser and just play
with the end result
um to get a feeling of uh what parts are
involved in creating
a microphone its application and not
only hearing about theoretical concepts
but also
playing around with with it modifying it
and moving on from there
when is your book expected to be
available so the book is currently
available in early access if you sign up
for the book
you can read all of the chapters and we
are currently
in the production stage so getting
everything ready to be
printed and it should be out this summer
we'll definitely have a link to your
book
in the show notes is there anything that
you've covered in the book that we
haven't talked about today
the book goes into detail on some
technical optimizations like
doing asset delivery and providing
caching but and also some
optimization strategies for for
performance but
as of the topics we just talked about i
think we covered
the big picture and talked about all of
the important aspects
michael how can people contact you they
can follow me on twitter or on github
under the name nultatis and i'm also
running a site which is called
micro-fondants.org where you can learn
more about the microphones architecture
we'll include a link to the website on
the show notes
it was really great having you here
today michael thank you so much
thanks for having me thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening